Hello, welcome. It is July 3rd or 4th
depending on where you are and we are in
active inference guest stream
110.1 with Tuya Isomeura discussing the
triple equivalence for the emergence of
biological intelligence. Previously, we
had some discussions in the live stream
51 series when we visited Area 51
together and we talked a lot about a
double equivalence and now the bar has
been raised, the increment has been
incremented and this is a really
exciting area that I'm sure we'll have a
lot to discuss and learn from. So, thank
you again for joining and looking
forward to the presentation.
Great. Um, thank you Daniel for
invitation. Um, so thank you for
inviting me for this uh guest talk of
active inference institute. I'm very
happy to share uh my recent paper on the
triple
equivalence. So let's get
start. So I'm interested in the theory
of intelligence in general. So maybe
baby had no uh such high uh intelligence
but through learning it obtain the
intelligence. This can be modeled or
understand in terms of the
self-organization of neuronet network.
The newborn neuronet network may don't
have may not have uh enough information
regarding the external world but through
some optimization which is typically
expressed in terms of the energy
minimization it achieve some
uh obtaining obtaining of some uh good
structure to recapturate the external
world which is the basis for prediction
and making insight or making creativity.
So we would like to model uh those
emergence of uh intelligent function
within the neural network uh through the
energy minimization formulation and so
far there are to my opinion there are
three major pillar in the theory of uh
intelligence.
So
intelligence occurs in the brain. So uh
we model the brain using a network of
neurons. And uh this is a a diagram of
electrical circuit and similarly a
single neuron can be modeled like this.
So this diagram represent a dynamical
equation of a single neuron and through
some approximation we can uh represent
such a dynamics in terms of the energy
minimization. So here the dynamics that
descent this energy gradient uh energy
landscape represent the time uh change
of the neural activity like this. So
this is the view uh from the dynamical
system. The another view of intelligence
is the
computation. So it is well known that
any algorithm uh can be expressed in
terms of the Turing machine. Turing
machine is a simple abstract machine
that express the computation. So uh
which involves uh finished state machine
that's some make some that make some
computation and there is a long tape. So
in the tape uh some information is
encoded. So like uh uh binary
signals and when uh this finished test
machine read uh this uh information uh
it um incorporate that information into
the uh of the this state machine header.
Uh so uh those component can be
expressed uh by uh mapping uh shown
here. So given the current state and
read out information it provides the
move and writing information and the
next state. So this is a basic idea uh
underlying the cheing machine and
interestingly this simple computation is
sufficient to express any kind of
computable algorithmic uh algorithms.
And another view uh recently focusing on
is uh the brain as the uh inference
machine. So brain is considered now as a
agent that perform basian inference. So
this is an example of the bijen or
statistical inference. So here there is
some apple uh nearby the wall. By seeing
that we don't see think that apple is
locked in the shape of wall but uh we uh
guess that uh this apple is hidden uh by
the wall in front of the apple. So this
is a kind of inference based on our
experiences. So this can be formulated
in terms of the basia inference. So bian
inference is basically
uh defined by
the equation called b theorem. So this
is the uh b theorem that tell us the
probability of state uh given we can
obtain the same solution by just
minimizing uh energy which is called
variational free energy in the basian
inference field.
So idea here is that so if we uh reduce
the uh state sorry if we change the
state uh to reduce this energy and then
if it reach the bar of this energy
landscape this point uh represent a
solution of B theorem. So instead of uh
directly computing equation by just uh
minimizing the energy we can get the
best guess about the external world and
this process is expressed by like like
this. So this is the idea behind the uh
theory called the free energy principle.
So free energy principle as you may know
a theory of the brain proposed by
Kristen which states that perception
learning and action of all biological
organ are determined to minimize
variational free energy and by doing so
they perform variational bas inference
for external world. Uh this animation is
uh the one I often use to explain the
frenzy principle framework. So here
there is a animal which is our agent
that infer the external world and
external world comprises observable
information and
unobservable information which is a
hidden state and the task for this agent
is to infer the hidden state based only
on observable information and uh by
constructing some prior belief in the uh
sorry By constructing the posterior
belief uh in the brain it can uh guess
uh what is the current hidden state and
this is can be done by minimizing the
free energy. So idea is that uh if we
change the uh posterior belief s uh uh
to minimize this landscape then we get
uh the optimal solution uh which is
called posterior uh belief or posterior
expectation and uh uh this is the
equation of the variational free energy.
it comprises uh prediction error term
and uh entropy or complexity
term. So uh to achieve this sort of
inference we also need to update the
model itself. So this is done by update
of the parameter theta. So in the
external world there is a some mapping
from hidden state to observation. So we
imitate uh this mapping uh using the
generative model. So by tuning this seat
our generative model is optimized to
recapturate the external world and then
we get the best guess about the hidden
state. This is the a mechanism
underlying the
perception and the an unique point of
the free energy principle is that it can
be applied also to the optimization of
action. So here we consider some the we
we consider that there is some uh
preference prior for this agent and to
achieve this uh sensory input uh this
agent can uh select an action uh from uh
given set. Here there are three options
and this optimization can be done by uh
minimizing the free energy in the
external uh free energy in the future
which is called expected free energy. So
except free energy is a function of
action. So by selecting the action uh
that achieve the minimum free energy
minimum expected free energy uh it can
maximize the probability to obtain the
preferred input in the future. So this
is the idea so-called active
inference. So like this uh free energy
principle is a normative theory uh that
can express both uh perceptual
optimization and action optimization.
But for uh neuroscientists like us uh
the most interesting point is the what
is the neuronal implementation
underlying those uh inference. So we
would like to uh show
uh actual neuronal implementation of
this sort of uh active inference. So to
address this issue uh we recently
proposed equivalence double equivalence
between uh neuron dynamics and basian
inference. So we start from evaluating
the neural activity equation. So
neuroactivity equation is uh have long
history. So it uh have a clear
biological background. So we consider
that this is a plausible one. And uh if
this equation is derived as a gradient
descent of some energy function, we can
obtain the original equation by just
taking the integral of this uh activity
equation and get uh energy uh which is
called hermo
energy. On the other hand uh for basian
inference once we define the model
generative model about the external
world we can derive the free energy
functional. This is a variation of free
energy and its minimization indicates
the achievement of bijia inference. we
show a mathematical equivalence between
those two uh energy
functions which means that for any
neural network in this class there is a
interpretation in terms of beta
inference. So we can in general see uh
neural activity or neuronet network
dynamics including synaptic plasticity
as uh inference about the external
state. So this is a more mathematical
definition of our equivalence. So we
characterize new activity equation using
some rate coding model which is derived
from uh realistic spiking model uh
through some approximation. So it uh
form is like this. It is characterized
by imbussing mode leak factor and uh uh
all indicate the sensory input from
input area. W is a synaptic weight. H is
the firing threshold and X here is a
vector of neural activity which is late
coding uh neurons and its dynamics is uh
given like this and if this is given
then we can consider the original uh
energy function by taking the integral
of this activity equation with respect
to x and we get
a explicit form of uh Helen horse energy
like this although it is little bit
complicated uh it's just the integral of
original equation
so not no not worry about that don't
worry about that and uh those uh
definition of bar is here and hat
indicate the sigmoid function of uh w
and uh uh phi is a threshold factor
defined like
case and interestingly although this
energy is purely derived from activity
equation the same energy provides the
plasticity equation. If we take the
derivative of this a with respect to w
then we get uh heian plasticity
equation. So this is nonrivial right um
this is purely derived from this
activity equation but it also provides
plasticity. Moreover for basian
inference uh once we define the
generative model we get the variational
free energy. So this is the variational
free energy under the assumption that
the generative model have the shape of
the partially observable marcoition
process or pomod. So if the external
world is expressed as a discrete state
space then we get this kind of
variational
energy and its minimization provides the
solution of bij inference which is a
posterior belief about state and we also
obtain the uh posterior belief about the
model parameter. So which correspond to
learning and what we say is that there
is a formal equivalence between those
two energy function in the sense that
each component have a one to one mapping
uh between those two. So s here
indicates the posterior expectation
about each state taking uh zero or one.
So it is expressed as the block vector
just like uh the block vector of x and
xar and this logarithm correspond to
this logarithm and this a actually have
the block matrix structure which is
exactly corresponding to this block
matrix. And this operation in a product
corresponding to this uh product of
matrix and vector and this log d which
is the state post state prior uh is
formally corresponding to uh five
here. So as a result we can say that for
any neural activity and plasticity in
this class that minimize the uh
common termhorse energy we can uh be uh
we can lead those dynamics in terms of
the basian inference of external states.
Okay. And moreover uh this framework uh
can be extended to the empirical
application. Uh so to apply the
theoretical framework into the empirical
data, we first record uh neuronal
activity from real
brain and uh we assign those data into
our canonical neural network which is
our network model and uh by taking the
integral we can get the underlying hero
energy which characterize the
neurodynamics and plasticity.
Moreover, uh we can estimate the
parameter from data uh to characterize
uh uh for characterize this energy
function for uh specific for
individual and through our established
equivalence we can get we can identify
the generative model and the
corresponding operational energy from
this
a and this works as a synthetic agent
that perform active inference. So it
derivative uh uh produce a learning
algorithm or plasticity algorithm that
uh update synaptic weight uh to adapt to
the environment and its time integral
provides uh prediction about the
learning process. So we call this
framework as a rebar engineering uh in
the sense that from neuro activity data
we can get the genative model which is a
blueprint for the individual animals. So
by doing that we can uh get a synthetic
agent that imitates the original
animal's m activity and behavior. So now
we can make the examination of the frey
principle.
Uh so our idea is that so we can uh do
this based only on neural activity in
the initial learning stage. So we we
record the neural activity before
training and characterize generative
model and make prediction of the
subsequent running process based on the
synthetic agents that perform active
inference. If its prediction is
consistent with uh new activity data
recorded after training then it
indicates the probability of the theory
underlying this synthetic agent. So if
this is the case then we can validate
the we can validate the predictive
validity of the free energy principle
and active inference. So this is the
idea.
So we apply this or uh we apply this to
uh in vitro neuronet network uh cultured
on a dish. So this is a neuron taken
from rat embryo and we culture those
neurons on a dish that have 64 electrode
at floor and we stimulate neuron those
neuron using designed uh sensory
signals. So which is the electrical
parts. So to stimulate uh neurons we uh
design those uh stimula stimulization
pattern uh using two hidden states. So
those are hidden status hidden sources
that is invisible for in vitro neural
networks.
So they can receive signal directly
receive signals only from sensory stimul
layer here. So by receiving those mixed
sensory signals those neuron are
required to infer the hidden state. So
if it can infer the hidden state then it
uh support the prediction and pregnancy
principle. So we test that and we found
that actually some neuron uh response
preferentially to a specific source. So
uh the prediction of frey principle is
correct in this setting and we also uh
statistically estimate the effective
connectivity between those neurons and
uh uh plot those trajectory. So synaptic
weights change during the training. So
we brought the that trajectory onto the
theoretically derived free energy
landscape. So this is the free energy uh
characterized only by the initial data
uh of this invitual learning experiment
and we now brought the trajectory onto
this. So this is the
empirically estimated synaptic weight
trajectory which uh started from the
high point of the landscape and it
reduced to the reduce uh the free energy
to reach the
bottom which is consistent with the
expectation of the free energy principle
that uh synaptic plasticity occur to
minimize the free energy. So yeah, it's
consistent. Uh if this is the case, we
can make synthetic agent that perform
frenzy uh minimization. So this is the
result of the simulator that just uh
exploit the gradient of this
theoretically computed free energy
landscape. So it is just a simulation
uh without using data. Nevertheless, its
result is highly consistent with actual
observation meaning that uh the theory
have the prediction ability in this
setting. So it shows the validity of the
freency
principle and then we extend our idea to
action optimization active. To optimize
action, we need to consider the
modulation of heavy plasticity because
our action is changed based on the given
reward or
punishment. So uh classically this sort
of uh optimization of action uh is
associated with the hepian prosticity
modulation by neurom modulator various
neurom modulator. One uh famous one is
the dopamineic modulation of heavian
type plasticity. So it change the timing
window of the STDP. So STDP here means
the uh spike timing dependent plasticity
which is a sort of uh heavy plasticity.
So it change dopamine change drastically
this window of STDP like this and we
incorporate those effect into the he uh
into the plasticity equation and we also
consider two layer recurrent neural
network uh with output layer to model uh
the action of
animals. So it is uh basically same uh
model as the previous one. Uh we call
this uh canonical neural network. And uh
one uh important uh characteristic of
this canonical neuronet network is that
all of those equations both neur
activity and plasticity can be derived
from a single energy function which
means that there is a corresponding
basian inference characterized by
variational free energy. So we again uh
get the one to one correspondence
between neurodynamics and bija inference
and interestingly this sort of neuron
can perform uh maze task. So this is a
typical delayed reward task but by uh
inferring the best action that obtain
the uh maximum reward in the future. So
which is uh in other words uh minimum
risk uh in associated with the future
outcome. Uh by doing so this network uh
can uh achieve uh the best uh action uh
to uh realize uh this main
task. So so far we show uh double
equivalence between neural network
dynamics and bas inference. So in
general uh neural network a canonical
neuronet network that minimize some
energy function by both activity and
plasticity it inevitably perform uh ba
inference active inference uh in some
sense. So uh frenazi principle is such a
generic uh general framework to
characterize uh this sort of biological
approach for neural network. The next
step is uh incorporation of the
algorithmic computation because so far I
discuss about um optimization perception
and action which is not
uh completely generic uh intelligence
form. So it is uh limited uh only for
optimizing uh behavior to obtain uh to
to minimize the future risk. But
question is whether this framework can
be applied to the emergence of a generic
intelligence generic
algorithm that's uh my interest. So to
address this issue
we proposed the triple coariance. We
show the triple equence between neural
network dynamics and variational vision
inference framework and the turing
machine. So here uh we have two cheing
machine one is internal turing machine
and one is external turing machine. So
instead of
characterizing environment in terms of
the gantium model uh we characterize the
the environment in terms of external
cheing machine but the point here is
that such a cheing machine can also be
implemented in terms of the probability
uh distribution. So which is actually
expressed in terms of generative model.
Uh I'm moreware because cheering machine
typically deal with the
uh deal with the discrete state space.
So this is expressed in the form of pom
dp. So we simply consider the pom dp
with some uh external tape. So this is
uh what I actually did. So to infer such
environment we have the uh cheing
machine which is basically have the same
shape as the external cheing machine and
we show that this type of cheing machine
can be implemented by uh canonical
neural network. So idea uh is that so we
first
uh characterize the canonical neuronet
network in terms of the energy function
like this and we also characterize
differentiable turing machine uh in
terms of in terms of the uh energy
minimization. So if we get if we write
uh Turing machine in some differential
equation by taking the integral uh we
can again obtain the energy function.
So and uh through this process we
confirm that actually the energy
function derived from touring machine is
equivalent to that for canonical neural
network. So this is this happened
because
uh output layer of canonical neuronet
network can be seen as a tape uh for
touring machine and this operation
reading out and writing uh into tape can
be implemented
uh in a biologically proible manner
through uh mental action that uh affect
some uh change for the internal state
and the writing can be implemented by
rapid plasticity of output layer uh
simot weight. So through those process
uh we can uh implement the function of
chewing machine which is the um reading
and writing and state update and header
position movement is also implemented by
the neur activity uh sparse neural
activity that expressed an address of
the
information. And uh once we get uh
energy function which is common for all
uh component in the system then we can
say that there is a corresponding
variation of free energy. So uh we found
that actually this sort of cheing
machine uh formally correspond to uh
kind of pom dp genative model and uh you
again uh this mapping from uh output to
uh state posterior correspond to uh read
out of uh information lead out of
information and uh if we rapidly change
the C matrix which is a policy matrix
that determined our action then uh this
uh act as memory writing. So rapid
change of uh policy uh can be seen as uh
writing of
information. So in short what we show is
that we characterize neural network in
terms of the energy minimization. So it
involves both neural activity and
plasticity. Interestingly, this typical
neuronet network dynamics can be lead as
both mapping uh of cheing machine and
bed
serum in the sense that so this is a
energy minimizing activity and uh if
energy is minimized with respect to
internal state of neural network then
this solution uh can be seen as the
solution of basian inference. which is a
bas and also in the
simultaneously it also represents
mapping uh this mapping which means that
uh this network is not limited to infer
the uh pom db typical to pom dbp in the
external world but also it can infer the
cheing machine in the external world and
imitate that function into uh uh inside
the network uh dynamics. So it can uh im
uh imitate uh mimic the external
algorithm using neural network dynamics.
So that's the idea. So uh based on this
generic framework uh we performed some
demonstration. So this is a uh
demonstration using other. So other
means a machine that add count up the
number. So here we provide the input as
the uh emin hand visit. So actually this
is only binary signal. So each uh
becomes either zero or one and this uh
16 16 uh binary uh number represents uh
inputs and the external che machine
count up those numbers and memorize that
sum uh into the tape. So this is what
the environment
works. Given this system, the internal
canonical neural network which perform
active inference can perform the
imitation of this dynamics by receiving
this 100 digit. It infer whether this is
zero or one through uh this uh layer and
the internal computation make addition
of those uh signal into the um previous
sumation of the uh which is uh stored in
the memory and the memory is actually
implemented by output layer neur output
layer synaptic weights. So here uh by
by given the internal state the middle
layer neur activity it uh send some
signal to output layer which correspond
to address of the uh information and
given this uh output layer activity
generate action. uh this weight
correspond to the memory uh in the tape
and it takes either zero or
one. So by by sending your signal header
information here uh it receive uh the
memory information and it feed back to
the internal states. So this is uh how
this network works as an other and the
writing of new information into the
output layer is done by heavy plasticity
modulated by uh risk factor.
So this uh plasticity occur in a rapid
manner. So that uh by receiving new risk
it uh drastically change the signup rate
either from 0 to one or one to zero
which is sufficient to implement uh the
lighting function of the cheing machine.
So this sort of neuron can implement a
cheering machine in a biologically
proible manner and uh this is a result
of inference. So by receiving hand res
hand uh digit which is uh noisy
information uh it can correctly infer
the hidden state uh like this and uh it
successfully store the information in
the output layer uh which represents the
summation of the number. So it count up
the input number and store that
here and through running the accuracy of
inferring uh hidden state and memorize
uh information uh sum some summit s some
number is improved.
So before training uh the estimated
number is largely different from the
true number but uh in these four
sessions uh which comprises uh
2,48 steps it achieved uh good inference
and uh uh this is a quantitative uh
evaluation of prediction error it
decrease uh with uh time increase and
also this network optimize its parameter
uh by minimizing free energy and uh uh
the parameter estimation error decrease
with time like
this. Okay. Um this is
a this is the demonstration of al
algorithmic implementation and inference
of external algorithm using canonical
neural network. However, there is some
limitation in this framework. So here we
assume a predefined learning uh sorry
predefined writing rule which is
implemented by risk function. So if we
can design uh risk function or which is
corresponding to expect free energy
apply okay then we can train the neural
network in a appropriate manner. But
question is whether uh those predefined
function can also be optimized through a
biologically proable uh process. That's
our next question. To address that we
consider uh extension of our framework
to the evolutional time scale. So
evolution occurs through the update of
gene and we associate that with the
update of model. So we now extend the
framework to the basian model selection
framework. So uh by updating the model
uh we get a better generative model and
based on that model we update parameter
through the scientific plasticity and
then infer the hidden state and action
uh through neur activity and its result
is evaluated and then uh it's uh
iterated so on. So we model this
framework using extended hermhor's
energy which is uh a function for a
species not the individual. So we now
define uh the distribution of agent like
this. So this represent uh distribution
uh or over observation sequence and gene
distribution. So which characterize uh
what kind of agent exist in our
environment okay and how what kind of
information received uh is received uh
by those agent. So we now consider the
populations. So this is defined uh by
adding uh some component to the
individual perm energy defined
previously. So this is um Hermho's
energy uh we discussed and uh we add
here to some factor. For example, this
uh represent the reproduction rate which
is the evolutional fitness function and
this is the uh parent gene distribution
which correspond to prior distribution
of
uh gene here. And this is um uh entropy
uh but it is representing it represent
um posterior belief uh about uh the
observation gene distribution. So it is
analogous to uh conventional variational
free energy but now we uh also optimize
the
model. So interestingly by uh taking the
derivative of this or taking the
variation of this uh functional we get a
solution like this. So this
solution of course it has a meaning in
terms of basian inference but it has
another meaning. So interestingly this
uh solution uh posterior belief
represents
uh uh is given as the product of uh
evolutional fit function and marginal
likelihood and the prior gene
distribution and this marginal
likelihood can be seen as the
observation uh conditioned by the gene.
So this result actually is equivalent to
uh the solution no uh natural selection
simple natural selection. So now we
found that uh by defining Herm energy
which is uh equivalent to variational
free energy uh and minimizing that we
get the solution of uh natural selection
in a
uh natural manner. So uh this indicate
that the solution of uh bijium model
section involves uh conventional natural
selection and uh this can be also
understand by this uh inequality. So
here it indicate that
uh population level perm energy or uh
variation of energy upper bounds uh this
factor. So this is a negative logarithm
of uh partition function z and
interestingly under this framework this
partition function uh correspond to the
total of offspring number. So uh
minimization of free energy uh provides
the maximization of total of offspring
number. So if uh this sort of uh agent
want to maximize their offspring then
it's
uh naturally minimize uh the free
energy. So that's uh what we uh
characterize by through those equations
and uh we confirm that um through this
process uh agent finally achieve the
species of agent finally achieve uh the
good model for making inference of the
given environment. So before the
evolution uh optimal gene correspond to
uh some machine that is different from
others. So its genes like this. So it's
operation provides a solution different
from others. But through training
through evolution only gene that
achieved the uh operation or mapping
which is correct as uh other uh survived
and after sufficient evolution through
40 generations uh finally uh most agent
uh converge to um machine that
perform as adults. So this is a result
of bianium model selection but uh it's
uh
more explicit uh it's more actively uh
select the best uh external world to
achieve the maximization of uh offspring
number. So it is uh called uh active uh
vision model selection and through this
process uh estimation error decrease and
uh also uh total number estimation error
decrease. So uh it's showed a successful
uh model selection uh by simply
operating natural selection.
And finally I I briefly mentioned about
that um this framework can also
implement universal cheing machine. So
universal tuning machine is little bit
uh more than conventional cheing machine
bit because it can imitate any other
cheing machine although it's abstract
definition implementation is very
straightforward. If we have two mental
action one represent data reading and
one represent program reading then we
can implement a universal cheing machine
using canonical neuronet network. This
machine can infer the environment even
though environment comprises 10
different uh machines. So given sensory
input it can guess which machine now
generate sensory input and select best
position of uh header or reading program
and by receiving a program written in
tape uh it gets the it characterize
internal computation uh in a adequate
manner. So it's very flexible neural
network and given this program it can
imitate uh the given uh uh it can
imitate the um the environmental current
environmental machine uh uh through this
process and uh here a different color
indicate a different machine and uh
black color indicate the position of
header that neuronet network uh
inferred.
So uh before training inference is
little bit noisy but after training it
success accurate uh inference and by
doing so uh parameterized dimension
error and model selection error decrease
and uh subsequently state prediction
error also decrease. So uh it su
successfully uh uh imitate 10 different
machine in the external world only in
the uh single neural network
architecture. So in summary uh we show
that the dynamics of canonical neural
network that minimize shared herh energy
can be cast as minimizing variational
energy. So it's basically perform active
inference in general and canonical
neuronet network with mental action and
rapid modulated plasticity can implement
cheing machine in a biologically proible
manner and perform variational ba
inference of external algorithm which is
expressed by turing machine. And if we
extend her energy minimization uh to the
evolutional scale uh then spacey level
hero energy uh minimization uh involves
natural selection. So that that process
uh can be naturally derived from uh
minimizing energy providing a possible
explanation uh for the emergence of
generic biological intelligence. So
finally I just uh briefly mentioned that
uh those uh programs uh I mean Matra or
Python codes are all available at my
GitHub page. So if you are interested in
please check that. Thank
you. Thank you. Awesome. A lot
to cover
there. For people watching live, they
can write a question in the chat. I
wrote down a few as well. So I'll just
sort of start in no particular
order. Are we seeking to find pairwise
transformational edges and then maintain
overall network equality through
transitive properties or do you see
these different equivalences as arising
from a more general form or notation?
Thank you question. So uh c can I see
that uh
comment by myself? I mean yep you give
me one second. Yes.
Yes. First part is little bit
complicated to me. pair-wise.
Oh, when you did the work in the double
equivalence and now with the triple
equivalence, do you seek to
uh find pair-wise strong
relationships and keep everything equal
through the transitive property? or do
you think that there could be a common
representation that has more of like a
hub and spoke
topology with a common underlying format
that then
is connected to each of these domains?
Um so I'm not sure if I'm correctly
understand the question but uh uh unlike
double equivalence which is uh
correspondence so in double equivalence
all neural network
property as long as it minimize shared
energy function it is always basia
inference. So there is
a set of basia inference. It is very
general and there is a sub population
which is biologically proible basian
inference. So all of those sub
suboration is involved in the generic
bij inference. So uh if we design
neuronet network uh that uh by by
considering the energy minimization then
it always is involved in uh generic
vision inference framework. On the other
hand cheing machine or in particular uh
universal cheering machine is special
one. So not all not all cheering machine
uh works as a universal cheering
machine. So we we may design some random
network or random machine and we can say
this is a chewing machine. It's not
uh it's not
uh mis I mean it's in some sense correct
in some sense it's correct but uh it's
not useful so far I mean universal uh
computation cheing completeness uh means
uh that computation computing machine
have sufficient ability to deal with uh
algorithm computation
So yeah that is something outside. Uh so
what we are now thinking is that there
is a group uh that achieved the beta
inference and there's another group uh
that performing complete computation and
uh there's some overlap here. So if we
focus on that that that would be
interesting uh to to consider the
emergence of high level
intelligence. I don't know.
Okay. Awesome. All right. I'm going to
paste into the chat so you can see it. I
just wanted to read this
uh this quotation from a right
I double check that
and
yeah, okay, this is a from a 2017
article by Andre Carpathy
uh called software 2.0. And so he wrote,
I sometimes see people refer to neural
networks as just another tool in your
machine learning toolbox. They have some
pros and cons. They work here and there
and sometimes you can use them to win
Kaggle competitions. Unfortunately, this
interpretation completely misses the
forest for the trees. Neural networks
are not just another classifier. They
represent the beginning of a fundamental
shift in how we develop software. They
are software 2.0. And then a later
section is it turns out a large portion
of real world problems have the property
it is significantly easier to collect
data or more generally identify
desirable behavior than to explicitly
write the program. Because of this and
many other benefits of software 2.0
programs that I will go into below. We
are witnessing a massive transition
across the industry where a lot of 1.0
code is being ported into 2.0 code.
Software 1.0 0 is eating the world and
now AI software 2.0 is eating
software. So how do you how do you think
the kinds of analytical and empirical
results that you're
yielding might play into how we think
about software engineering and designing
different kinds of intelligent systems?
That's that's very interesting. uh
question.
Um
yeah. Um
right.
So so thought of neuronet network we I
I'm I'm working on is uh yeah largely
different from the state of uh deep
learning machines. So we are more
focusing on how uh the re real
brain how real brain works uh when it's
doing some uh computation or making
decision and uh yeah although uh the
large gap between the the neuronet
network model in computational
neuroscience which is too simple and the
um state of state object AIS. So we we
think that if we want to examine whether
what we are doing is correct as the
model of the brain then um what we are
doing it have meaning because so when we
want to do some task for animals
nonhuman animals only they can do this
just a simple task.
And to my uh belief to my uh experiences
most of those task can be implemented by
simple pomod architecture and some
require some extension. But basically uh
what we are dealing with here is
sufficient to characterize what uh
animals doing in the system neuroscience
uh sense. So yeah, beyond that we may be
able to consider some uh more
functioning uh neuronet networks through
our strategy but uh it is it it is not
not soon. So we need
uh yeah many other validation before uh
going to that step.
What does the reverse engineering as you
have it in the GitHub or as you imagine
this developing, what does it
yield that a systems biology assessment
wouldn't?
You mean you what is uh sorry can can
you rephrase that? Yeah. What do we gain
and learn from the reverse engineering?
Uh right that just a circuit level
dissection doesn't provide.
Yeah. So circuit level dissection
basically provide us uh static
information right information about
architecture neural operation
uh at that point. So we see um snapshot.
So what we are interested in is more
prediction things. So uh through reverse
engineering we get a genative model
which has uh so it have learning ability
it itself is agent. So instead of making
connetoics or making some uh the
characteristic of static neuronet
network we can characterize the dynamics
of neural network in terms of generative
model. It provides us a prediction of
long-term future after some learning. So
which is completely different from what
uh conventional system neuron science
does.
Okay, another question. I put it in the
chat. So how do we reconcile the
traditionally essentially
errorfree nature of touring machines and
digital
computation with the more fundamentally
probabilistic nature of neural and
basian systems
like part part of the reason why the
symbolic architectures are useful is
because they can be used
deterministically. So are we seeking
something that's deterministic or
probabilistic?
Yeah, thank you for asking that. So it
is related to our demonstration using uh
others and uh uh 100 digit uh numbers.
So 100 digit uh your noisy uh stochastic
information and once we our network
uh extract the the hidden features from
such a stoastic information then hidden
layer is become uh becoming more uh
deterministic in the sense that if we
accumulate sufficient information the
pom db model becomes either zero or one
state, right? So in that case uh the
state transition can be very uh
deterministic. Of course we in general
we need to deal with the stoastic uh
stochastic um
environment but yeah sometimes either uh
likelihood matrix or uh transition
matrix can be deterministic and uh under
that situation uh our machine uh
provides
uh very accurate uh
prediction about states current state or
future state. And moreover,
although
conventional naive cheinging machine is
very deterministic or discrete uh but um
differential cheing machine incorporate
uh the current uh continuous dynamics
and discrete uh chewing machine. So it
is a cheing machine that is expressed by
the differential equation and we extend
uh that idea to the energy minimization
in the sense that differential turing
machine uh of us is derived as the
gradient descent on some energy. So this
dynamics is something between the the
discretized uh symbolic computation and
uh continuous dynamics and based on the
condition just like inbas temperature
parameter we can sift uh that dynamics
both to uh discretized symbolic
computation and continuous dynamics.
That's the idea underlying what we are
doing.
Great.
Okay. So, in computer science theory,
the halting problem or Turing's halting
problem is the description that uh or
the problem that the description of a
computer program and the input you
cannot determine whether the program
will finish running or run forever. So
if we can make this kind of software 2.0
neural network
representation and or like this software
question mark with the basian
interpretation as
well. Are they also bound by some of
these constraints? Or do you think there
could be some angles of approach where
problems that are not solvable in a
procedural computational framework could
be approached
probabilistically and vice versa?
Yeah, thank you for the question. Yeah.
uh the simple answer is I don't know the
the exact answer but so I I try to make
my opinion so um yeah first of all
although we consider some neuronet
network that perform cheering machine so
it it is
uh still in the framework of chewing
machine or chat chewing t in the sense
that yo what we are doing with just uh
computation based on algorithms right
you even though we are designing very
realistic brain model comprising hosin
hack spiking neuronet network so it
isn't just algorithm so it is
implemented in terms of cheing machine
so in that sense nothing different but
uh and uh it it means that we do not
solve the hurting problem. So our
network can uh conclude whether this
program is finished or not. However, we
can guess whether this is a good
strategy or bad strategy. So one
interesting difference from the
conventional turing machine is that this
our neural network works in a real time.
So time is uh passing uh during a
computation unlike cheering machine a
conventional cheering machine. So which
means that if we select a b strategy
that does not stop uh during the
meaningful time frame then that animal
that synthetic animal die or
eliminated through the natural selection
stage. So uh survived species should be
uh should have some uh meaningful
function meaningful algorithm that works
in a realistic time frame. So yeah that
works as some debac or selection of
algorithm. So that is what I'm thinking.
Yeah, the the connections with the
neural Darwinism are very interesting
and also the open-endedness of
successful life. It's like those are the
programs that haven't halted and you
don't know whether the environment could
change and they could all of a sudden
die. But what you know by observing
their existence is that they haven't
halted yet. So it's like one sense
they're able to carry out a computation
in plausible time and on the other hand
their persistence as a species as a
population
is still
running. Um so how will you proceed from
here? What what directions do you plan
to follow?
Um the plan yeah the plan involves
some emergence of new algorithm. I I
mean yeah algorithm. So now we have mean
to implement represent uh arbitrary
algorithm within the neuronet network
architecture which is corresponding to
extended pom dp. And uh what now we are
interested in is whether the function
that
can the the function those uh network
can do is only limited to uh imitation
of external world or it can do something
different from the simple imitation of
external world. So if the internal AL
algorithm itself have some new meaning
then that will be more interesting.
What would that look like or how will
you explore that?
Yeah, it's a difficult question. M and
what what can happen within a fixed
topology of a baze graph or neural
network or program information flow and
then what is possible when the structure
of the network
changes because there's a space of
semantics that can be
explored with the quantitative variation
just through the weight updating
and then there's another shell of
possibility ility based upon topological
change.
That's true. That's true. So for
example, we now we do not involve uh
structural plasticity uh within uh
lifetime but the model selection done by
update of gene involves the change of
the size of network. You know by by
changing the gene we can freely uh
change the number of neuro involving
network or whether it is a two layer or
three layer like that. So anything can
be characterized by gene and it
selection means the uh model selection
uh from
the yeah very various model types. So,
so I I mean yeah in principle we can
consider many things but question is
whether it is proible. I mean it yeah
intuitively it requires very high
computational cost uh you know it is
something like a random search in the uh
huge binary space. So as you may know
yeah uh
combinator optimization takes uh
exponential time. So question is whether
animals do that or animals know better
searching algorithm or animal avoid to
do that and yeah have another uh
solution. So that kind of things is very
interesting to me.
Cool. Is there anything else you want to
add?
Um yeah. So although I I'm not fully
sure whether we can uh validate uh the
cheing machine uh relationship between
cheing machine basia inference and
neuronet network using real data. At
least we can uh validate uh the double
equivalence between neuronet network and
the bij inference and we can be extend
some something to the evolutional uh
direction or trig machine direction. So
yeah I think as the neuroscience I I I
think I'm a theoretical neuroscientist.
So as the neuroscience we need to do
both developing development of the
theory and validation of theory uh they
are interact with each other. So uh I'm
very interested in both site and if you
are interested in this sort of research
I'm very happy to working with you.
Thank you. Last question. Do you think
there's a
fourth player at that intersection?
Yes, that uh that very interesting
question. So, so one thing which I'm
used to be interested in is
consciousness things. So yeah many
people nowadays interested in
consciousness and there are several
theory of consciousness
but as long as I know those three
pillars uh neuronet network ba inference
and touring machine algorithm
computation does not in do not involve
uh consciousness idea so I'm want to ask
some expert that whether consciousness
can be involved in those framework or it
is different from those framework. Maybe
that can be a horse
pure.
Awesome. Okay. Thank you very much for
joining. It's exciting to see how things
have developed with the empirical work
and this new theoretical layer as well
since a few years ago. So looking
forward to where you take it from here.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
Bye. Bye.